Guide to the Leslie Koempel Papers, 1937-1972
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Leslie Koempel Papers
1937-1972
Koempel, Leslie Alice, 1907-
20.5 cubic feet (25 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Material relating to Koempel's work as a sociologist and a professor at Vassar College. Of particular interest is the data she compiled relating to education and housing in Poughkeepsie and Dutchess County.
Biographical Note
Leslie Alice Koempel (1907-1995) taught in the Sociology Department at Vassar College from 1946-1972. She did her undergraduate work at the University of California, and her doctoral work at Bryn Mawr. Before coming to Vassar, she taught at Skidmore, Rockford and Mount Holyoke colleges. Much of her work focused on Poughkeepsie and Dutchess County. She had a particular interest in education and housing.
Scope and Content Note
Survey data, correspondence, and reports relating to Koempel's work as a sociologist and a professor at Vassar College. Of particular interest is the data she compiled relating to education and housing in Poughkeepsie and Dutchess County.
Access
Special permission is required for research using the raw survey data in this collection. The rest of the collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Vassar College Field Work Records
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College. Department of Sociology
Subjects:
Education--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Housing--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Places:
Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--Statistics
VCL Categories:
Local History; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, June 2012.
Acquisition Information
Koempel's dissertation was given to the Library at an unknown date. The rest of the collection was transferred from a Vassar College storage area in 2012. [M2012-003]
Series List
- Series I. Subject Files, Biographical Material, and Writings, 1937-1972; (Boxes 17-18, 25)
- Series II. Survey Data, 1945-1969; (Boxes 1-16, 19-24)
Container List
- Series I. Subject Files, Biographical Material and Writings
  - Biography — Resumes and activity reports (Box 17)
  - Biography — "Evidence of work in community" (Box 17)
  - Biography — Vassar contracts (Box 17)
  - Biography — Professional correspondence (Box 17)
  - Biography — Personal correspondence (Box 17)
  - Biography — School notes (Box 17)
  - Koempel's Bryn Mawr Dissertation: "Measurement of Changes in the Standard of Living During a Depression,", 1937; (4 folders) (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous speeches and essays (Box 17)
  - Random lectures and articles (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - "Why Get Married?" (Box 17)
  - Vassar Sociology Department Report, circa 1966 (Box 17)
  - Economics 103/104 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 151 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 250 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 254 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 257 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 300/301, 1966-1968 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 355 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 359, 1960-1962 (Box 17)
  - Sociology 360/381 (Box 17)
  - Urban Studies, 1969-1972 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous course material (Box 17)
  - Vassar-Yale Department of Sociology (Box 17)
  - Mellon Reports (Box 17)
  - Vassar Summer Institute — Community Organization (Box 17)
  - Vassar Summer Institute — International Affairs, 1957 (Box 17)
  - Vassar Summer Institute Proposals, 1970-1971 (Box 17)
  - Summer School — Poverty, 1972 (Box 17)
  - What It Was Like at Vassar for Sociologists, 1958-1972 (Box 17)
  - Horizons Unlimited —The Second Year at Vassar, 1965 (Box 17)
  - Joseph Kirk Folsom, 1960 June (Box 17)
  - Recommendations [RESTRICTED] (Box 18)
  - The Sanford Report [Women and Education] (Box 18)
  - Vassar College Community Cooperation Project (Box 18)
  - Eastern College Conference on College Community Relations, 1953 (Box 18)
  - College-Community Relations (Box 18)
  - Need for a Youth Bureau in Dutchess County, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Dutchess County Libraries — Maisry MacCracken Study (Box 18)
  - "A Library and It's Community: A Study of the Adriance Library…" (Box 18)
  - Volunteer Groups in Poughkeepsie (Box 18)
  - Poughkeepsie Housing — Vacancy Study, 1947 (Box 18)
  - Poughkeepsie Housing Authority (Box 18)
  - Poughkeepsie Rental Housing Survey, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Smith Apartments Tenant Attitudes (Box 18)
  - Survey of Heating and Utilities used by Poughkeepsie Residents (Box 18)
  - Poughkeepsie Recreation Study, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Poughkeepsie Riot of July 27-28, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Do We Need a Community College in Dutchess County (Box 18)
  - Dutchess County Field Leadership Survey (Box 18)
  - A Study of Newcomer Families in the Raymond Avenue School District, 1969 (Box 18)
  - Women — Abortive Leslie Koempel study for AAUP (Box 18)
  - A Proposal for a Central Field Work office at Teachers College, Columbia University, 1955 (Box 18)
  - The Coreyville Settlement: A Report to the West Mountain Society, 1959 (Box 18)
  - Coreyville Settlement (Box 18)
  - Do You Want a Child In Your Home? (Box 18)
  - If an Unmarried Mother Consults Me, What Do I Do? (Box 18)
  - Social Myth as an Obstruction to Social Action, 1955 (Box 18)
  - Introduction to Sociology — Merton, 1948 (Box 18)
  - Understanding Human Nature (Box 18)
  - Depression — Caroline Bird (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous City of Poughkeepsie reports (Box 25)
- Series II. Survey Data [RESTRICTED]
  - Poughkeepsie Land Use Survey, 1945; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Kingston Religious and Social Survey, 1948; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Kingston Religious and Social Survey, 1948; (survey cards) (Boxes 19-22)
  - Voluntary Associations in Poughkeepsie and Dutchess County, 1949; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Rhinebeck Religious and Social Survey, 1949; (7 folders) (Boxes 1-2)
  - Survey of Job Experience and School Training of Poughkeepsie High School Students, 1949; (20 folders) (Boxes 2-4)
  - Survey of Job Experience and School Training of Poughkeepsie High School Students, 1949; (20 folders) (Boxes 15-16)
  - Survey of Job Experience and School Training of Poughkeepsie High School Students, 1949; (2 ledgers) (Box 24)
  - Poughkeepsie Neighborhood Survey, 1950; (25 folders) (Boxes 4-5)
  - Hudson Community Survey, 1950-1951; (23 folders) (Boxes 5-7)
  - Poughkeepsie Neighborhood Survey Maps, 1950 (Box 24)
  - Poughkeepsie Census Map, 1960 (Box 24)
  - City of Poughkeepsie Survey, 1952; (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Your City Government Wants to Know Survey, 1952; (12 folders) (Box 25)
  - Poughkeepsie Library Survey, 1953; (13 folders) (Boxes 7-8)
  - Smith Apartments Survey, 1954-1955; (13 folders) (Boxes 8-9)
  - Smith Apartments Survey, 1954-1955; (1 ledger) (Boxes 24)
  - Dutchess County Community College Survey, 1955-1957; (39 folders) (Boxes 9-12)
  - Dutchess County Community College Survey, 1955-1957; (11 folders) (Boxes 16-17)
  - Out of School Activities Survey, 1958; (30 folders) (Boxes 12-14)
  - Arlington School District Survey, 1969; (11 folders) (Boxes 14-15)
  - Poughkeepsie Adult Education Survey, undated; (1 ledger) (Box 24)